Norman Macleod Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Norman Macleod Collection
1947-1985
YCAL MSS 751
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.92
(9 boxes)
Macleod, Norman, 1906-1985
Norman Wicklund Macleod (1906-1985)
Norman Wicklund Macleod, poet, author, professor, and editor of Pembroke Magazine, was born in Salem, Oregon in 1906. He graduated from the University of New Mexico wtih a B.A. in 1930, with further studies at the University of Southern California, the University of Oklahoma, and Teachers College of Columbia University, where he received an M.A. in 1936. He began a lifelong career as a poet and editor in the 1920s, contributing to several "little magazines" and later becoming editor of Briarcliff Quarterly and founding editor of Pembroke Magazine. Among his book-length publications are Horizons of Death (New York: Parnassus press, 1934), Pure as Nowhere (Columbus, Ohio: Golden Goose, 1952) and Selected poems of Norman Macleod (Boise, Idaho: Ahsahta Press, 1975). Macleod taught English and creative writing at several colleges and universities in the United States, as well as the University of Baghdad, Iraq, before becoming Professor of English at Pembroke State University in Pembroke, North Carolina. Macleod died in 1985 in Greeneville, North Carolina.
Biographical information from May, Hal (ed.) Contemporary Authors. Volume 116. Detroit: Gale Research Company, 1986. p. 297.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by gift from various sources, 1977-2004. For further information, see notes at the level of each acquisition.
Scope and Contents
The Norman Macleod Collection consists of correspondence, writings, and a film that document the life and career of Norman Macleod, American poet and literary editor. The bulk of the collection consists of letters to associates and former students, including Richard Peabody, Jr., William A. Hunt, and Ruth Peck. Also present is a home movie of Macleod and his daughter Skye.
Conditions Governing Access
Box 4 (Super 8 film): Restricted fragile material. Reference copy may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Arrangement
Organized under six headings, in order of acquisition: December 1977 Acquisition, February 1978 Acquisition, 1982-1983 Acquisitions, November 1986 Acquisition, August 1993 and June 1994 Acquisitions, and September 2004 Acquisition.
American literature -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Periodical editors -- United States; Audiovisual materials; Super 8; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Periodical editors -- United States -- 20th Century; Hunt, William, 1944-; Macleod, Norman, 1906-1985; Peck, Ruth
- December 1977 Acquisition, 1947-1954; 0.42; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  This acquisition consists of manuscripts, correspondence and printed items by Norman Macleod, from the collection of Richard Wirtz Emerson. Manuscripts include poems by Macleod, sent to Richard Wirtz Emerson.
  Custodial History
  From the collection of Richard Wirtz Emerson.
  - Pure as Nowhere, typescript, 5 versions, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Adams Off Ox, typescript, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Thanks For Nothing, draft, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Family of Falling Apart, typescript, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Poems by Macleod, sent to Richard Wirtz Emerson, typescript, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters to Richard Wirtz Emerson, 1947-1952 (Box 1, Folder 6-10)
  - Golden Goose Magazine, no.4, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Supplement to the application of Norman Macleod" (curriculum vitae), undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- February 1978 Acquisition, 1977; 0.21; (1 box)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of James Grimes, 1978.
  This acquisition consists of copies of letters from Norman Macleod to James Grimes, concerning the history of Pembroke Magazine.
  - Letters to James Grimes (photocopies), 1977 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- 1982-1983 Acquisitions, 0.21; (1 box)
  This acquisition consists of letters from Norman Macleod to Richard Peabody, Jr., Sanford J. Smoller, and the Head of the English Department at Oklahoma College for Women.
  - Letter to Richard Peabody, Jr. (photocopy), 1982 July 6 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Gift of Richard Peabody Jr., 1982.
  - Letter to Sanford J. Smoller, 1982 November 29 (photocopy), undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Gift of Sanford J. Smoller, 1983.
  - Letter to "Dear Sir or Ms." (Head of the English Department, Oklahoma College for Women), 1983 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Gift of Martha Woltz, 1983.
- November 1986 Acquisition, circa 1974
  Gift of Victor Dalmas, 1986.
  - Home movie of Norman Macleod and his daughter, Skye, circa 1974; One reel of Super 8 film. (Box 4, Folder 17)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Box 4 (Super 8 film): Restricted fragile material. Reference copy may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
- August 1993 and June 1994 Acquisitions, 1974-1985; 1.67; (4 boxes)
  Gift of William A. Hunt, 1993-1994.
  The August 1993 and June 1994 Acquisitions consist of letters from Norman Macleod to William (Liam) A. Hunt, a former student and assistant. The letters discuss editorial projects, past and present, and Norman Macleod's legacy.
  - Letters to William A. Hunt, 1974-1981 (Box 5, Folder 18-22)
  - Letters to William A. Hunt, 1982-1984 (Box 6, Folder 23-27)
  - Letters to William A. Hunt, 1984-1985 (Box 7, Folder 28-31)
  - Letters to William A. Hunt, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 32-34)
  - Other papers found with correspondence, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 35)
- September 2004 Acquisition, 1974-1983; 0.21; (1 box)
  Gift of Edward Tate, 2004.
  This acquisition consists of letters from Norman Macleod to Ruth Peck, discussing travels, especially to Scotland and Europe, visits, editorial projects, and financial matters.
  - Letters to Ruth Peck, 1974-1984 (Box 9, Folder 36-42)